Today's Sutta is the Majjhima Nikaya
Salekha Salekha Sutta.
So, Majjhima Nikaya 8 Salekha Sutta as
we translated wearing away.
So, thus have I heard. At one time, the
auspicious one was staying near Savatthi
in Jeta's Grove, Anathapindika's
Monastery. In the late afternoon, venerable Maha
In the late afternoon, venerable Maha
Cunda came out of retreat and went to
the auspicious one.
He bowed and sat to one side and said to
the auspicious one,
he said to the auspicious one,
um
"Venerable sir, there are many different
views that arise in the world connected
with the assertions about the self or
the world.
Does the abandoning and relinquishing of
those views come about in a bhikkhu who
attends merely to the fundamentals of
the training?"
And then the Buddha repeats, uh "Cunda,
there are many different views that
arise in the world uh connected with
assertions about the self or the world.
A bhikkhu relinquishes and abandons
these views by seeing as it is with the
right understanding.
Um where they arise, where they settle,
and where they operate as this is not
mine, I'm not this, this is not myself.
So, full understanding of the views is
the way to relinquish them.
So then, the Buddha goes on and says,
"It is possible that a certain bhikkhu,
having thoroughly withdrawn himself from
sensuality, having withdrawn from
unbeneficial phenomena, with thinking
and with pondering with joy and ease
born of that withdrawal, might abide
having entered upon the first jhana.
He might think he's practicing wearing
away as in like um wearing away of
defilements. But in the training of the noble ones,
But in the training of the noble ones,
these are not called wearing away, i.e.,
the first jhana is not called the
wearing away, it's called easeful
abiding in the present experience.
So then he goes on to say, "It is
possible that some bhikkhu with the
appeasement of thinking and pondering,
with internal confidence and
collectiveness of mind,
without um thinking and pondering Wait,
what? It is possible that some bhikkhu with
It is possible that some bhikkhu with
the appeasement of thinking and
pondering Aha.
With the appeasement of thinking and
pondering, with internal confidence and
collectiveness of mind, without thinking
and pondering, with joy and ease born of
composure, might enter upon the second
jhana. So, with appeasement of thinking and
So, with appeasement of thinking and
pondering, the thinking and pondering is
without He's without
and he can then uh experience joy and
ease born born of that composure and
abide in the second jhana.
He might think he's practicing wearing
away, but in the training of the noble
ones, these are not called wearing away,
they're called easeful abidings in the
present experience.
Same goes for the third jhana.
Same goes for the fourth jhana.
I have to read it all.
And then he goes even further. He says
that it is possible that some bhikkhu
having fully surmounted perceptions of
form, with the ending of perceptions of
with the ending of perceptions of
resistance, not attending to the
perceptions of multiplicity,
knows that space is infinite, might
abide having entered upon extent of that
infinite space. He might think this is
practicing wearing away,
but in the training of the noble ones,
these are not called wearing away, they
are called peaceful abidings.
Goes further into the fully surmounting
the extent of infinite space, knowing
that consciousness is infinite,
abiding uh upon the extent of infinite
consciousness, but that too is not
wearing away.
Then, having fully surmounted the extent
of infinite consciousness, knowing that
there is nothing, might abide having
entered upon the extent of that
nothingness. Again, that too is not wearing away.
Again, that too is not wearing away.
It's just a peaceful abiding.
And then it is possible that some
bhikkhu having fully surmounted the
extent of nothingness might abide
uh entering upon the extent of neither
perception or nor non-perception
and he might think he's practicing
wearing away, but in the training of the
noble ones, these are not called wearing
away, they're called peaceful abidings.
So then, the Buddha goes to explain what
actually is
wearing away of the defilements.
So it says it is here children that
wearing away should be practiced like
this. Others will be cruel,
but here we will not be cruel.
Others will kill living creatures, but
we will not kill living creatures.
Others will steal, but we will not
steal. Uh others will not be celibate.
Others will not be celibate, but we will
be celibate. Others will lie, we won't
lie. Others will speak divisively, speak
harshly, engage in frivolous talk, we
won't speak divisively, speak harshly,
or engage in frivolous talk.
Others will be covetous,
we'll deal with
we won't be covetous, and we will not
have ill will.
Others will have wrong view, we'll have
the right view. Others have wrong
intention, wrong speech, wrong action,
wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong
recollection, wrong composure composure, wrong
wrong composure composure, wrong
knowledge. So, the wrong the non
the noble eight-fold path.
Um
Others will have wrong liberation, we
will have the right liberation. Others
will be overcome with indolence and
lethargy, we will we rid of indolence
and lethargy.
Others will be restless, we will not be
restless. Others will have doubts, be
irritable, be resentful,
will denigrate, be contentious, be
jealous, be stingy, be devious,
deceitful, obstinate, arrogant.
We won't be any of that.
Others will be hard to admonish, but we
will not be hard to admonish.
Others will have bad friends, we won't
have we will have good friends. Others
will be negligent, we will be diligent.
Others will be faithless, we will have
faith. Others will be shameless, we will
be ashamed of wrongdoing.
Others will be imprudent, we will be
prudent. Unlearned, we will be learned.
Lazy, we will be effortful.
Others will have muddled recollection,
we will have recollection properly
established. Others will be witless.
Others will be witless.
Um,
we will be accomplished in
understanding. And others will be attached to their own
And others will be attached to their own
views, holding them firmly, refusing to
let them go, but we will not be attached
to their own views, not holding them
firmly, but will let them go easily.
So, before I go further, let's just go
through this part.
Um, so, as you can see, like
jhanas are not the wearing away.
And instead of these kind of
well, almost like mundane things, you
know, like everybody knows, okay, we
shouldn't be cruel, we shouldn't lie,
steal. How is that wearing away?
Cuz surely enough, you know, if you look
at the uh
just you know, the the vast majority of
Buddhist instructions today, the
practice is, you know, the meditation,
the jhana, and the meditative
experiences. Um
Um
but not according to this sutta,
obviously not according to the other
suttas, but anyway, just if you look at
this sutta, you realize that
having developed jhana rightly, being
withdrawn from sensuality, being
withdrawn from hindrances, with thinking
and pondering both of the uh pleasure
and joy and born of that seclusion,
that is the result
of the right strivings, of the right
efforts, of the right surmountings, of the right
of the right surmountings, of the right
contemplations.
So, that's why first jhana, second
jhana, third jhana, fourth jhana, not
that oh, they're they're
uh irrelevant, or they're they're
pointless, or secondary. No, it's just
they're pretty much already types of a
fruit of the right effort. So, if a
person is rightly contemplating the
dangers of sensuality as that Anguttara
Nikaya early one says, I can't remember
the number,
says basically that one can enter jhana
having not
understood the danger gratification and
the escape in regards to sensuality,
that's not possible.
So, you could see that's the work.
That's the wearing away.
Uh diligence, diligent contemplation of
the the hindrances and wholesome states.
Not abstractly. And that's where this
second part, the exposition of wearing
away, kind of um hammers it in. It's not
like theoretical spreading of
loving-kindness and wishing well
everybody and so on. No, no, it's like
literal daily choices that you make by
body, speech, and mind that pertain to
cruelty, killing, stealing, not being
celibate, lying, speaking divisively,
harshly, frivolously,
uh harboring covetousness, ill will
mentally. Those are choices that you're
accepting. So, the mind, as I say often,
can come up with these things.
And you can't prevent that.
But you can certainly prevent adding
more fuel to that fire through your own
non-diligent, ignorant, wrongly emphasized choices.
ignorant, wrongly emphasized choices.
So, that's kind of the point. See,
others will be cruel. Like, the whole
world can be cruel. The whole world can find
can be cruel. The whole world can find
justifications
for killing, stealing, lying, speaking
divisively. I won't do it.
I won't do it.
Doesn't matter the reason. I won't do
it. So, I won't choose it.
I will be presented with an option. I
could be cruel. I could be harsh. I
could be rude. I could be disrespectful.
I could be uh killing, stealing. I could
not I could not be celibate. But I won't
do it.
That's the difference.
That's the training, as we often say, as
the suttas repeat left and right.
Um
exercising the right choices towards
skillful by body, speech, and mind, not
just adopting them
um because the authority told you it so,
but because you are actually wanting to
train your citta
through those choices, i.e., those
actions or abstaining from certain
actions. So, that's like same like that other uh
So, that's like same like that other uh
sutta, I think it may be the Majjhima as
well, where it was those different arahants
where it was those different arahants
when they listed um
when they were asked like, "What's the
most amazing thing? What's the single
thing that everybody should develop?"
And then they kind of listed their
abilities, they were kind of uh that
they developed in the process of
arahantship. Uh and then the Buddha came, and then
Uh and then the Buddha came, and then
they ask him, and he says, "Yeah, what I
all of you which is, you know, he was a
jhana master, he was this, he was that,
he was the four brahmaviharas." He says,
"Yeah, yeah, all that's great, but
actually the most correct answer that uh
um
one factor that is the most important was
factor that is the most important was
none of those special powers and results
and and liberations, it was the
diligence. Because it was the diligence as a factor
Because it was the diligence as a factor
that made them individually develop all
those uh amazing things.
And this is kind of the same, like you
think like, "Oh, first jhana, second
jhana." It's like,
"That's the correct result
of uh of correct practice."
So, by all means, it should be uh
strived for. Like, you should by all
means make the effort to withdraw your
mind from hindrances and sensuality, to
to remove the weight of sensual desire
from your citta.
But that's the work. But you could see
like if somebody develops that and then
abides in a state that basically cheetah
is not touched by that prison
danger all those similes that the first
Jana described one can think like oh wow
this is that purification this is that
this is what's bringing me to Arahan
ship and and we said well actually no it was
and and we said well actually no it was
the work that you did beforehand that
led you to that point that's why in that
another suit that he actually says
like it was a suit that it says that
it was a suit that it says that
basically Arahan ship can be
attained on the base of first Jana
second Jana third or fourth
which is kind of used to
to show that yes you need to have
at least the first Jana to the extent
necessary for the Arahan ship
but then the Buddha described it says
like you you you will have a monk or
something who would be
who develops the first Jana and abides
in it and then I would tell him
after that
that okay now regard everything in that
first Jana everything that's skillful
noble cleansed debt-free regard that as
peril dot that as everything else you
regard basically it's all the ways you
regard a sensuality they led you towards
the first Jana now continue regarding
the first Jana in that way as well
why so that his mind completely turns
away from that noble state so to speak
because then it will be impossible to
return anything lower than that
so that's that kind of exercising the
right choice recognizing the
the choice that's influenced by
lust aversion distraction
obviously food is how many 44 or
something all these other negative
factors but obviously they all boil down
to exercising the choice that's still
like either rooted in ignorance rooted in
either rooted in ignorance rooted in
complacency rooted in lack of diligence
rooted in lack of contemplation or not.
And you don't have to and the why this
suit is so good is because you don't
have to wait. Oh, I've got to wait for
the first Jana
to to to practice those first Jana then
I'll start exercising all of these right
practices. No, these right practices is
what's leading you in the direction of
Jana anyway.
So, on a day-to-day basis, whenever you
are presented
with a choice to follow wrong intention
or to abstain from it.
What do you do?
Whenever you are presented to engage in
frivolous talk,
to relish it,
to enjoy it,
do you follow it or do you say, "No,
I'll abstain from it."?
Whenever the mind wants to speak behind
someone's back,
derive satisfaction from speaking
divisively or gossiping,
do you accept it? Do you accept that
offer? Do you accept that possibility?
Or you say, "No."
Or or you not you don't forget what
should be recollected and where the
emphasis should be. That's the training.
Body, speech, and mind.
I mean, it can't be any clearer. This
suit that cannot summarize it in any
clearer manner
than this as to what is the training
that leads to the complete purification
of the mind and liberation and Jana and
everything else.
And that's exactly why I like see it
goes after after the Buddha goes to all
these describing of what actually is
wearing away, the next section is the
exposition of by intent.
I choice.
So, all of these are choices that people
all of these are choices that people
make. And that's why I keep saying
that's the difference between
having your mind say come up with a
choice, options for you. Ooh, I could be
options for you. Ooh, I could be
non-celibate on this occasion. I could
say a lie on this occasion.
That's not your problem. That's not your
choice. Your choice is do you accept the given
Your choice is do you accept the given
options?
Or do you exercise the correct
recollectedness and wisdom of
maintaining the context and the emphasis
or No, no, no, these choices lead away
from purification. These choices don't.
So, that's why the next the next section
says, "Chunda, I say that even the arising of
"Chunda, I say that even the arising of
intent towards beneficial qualities is
very helpful, let alone following that
embodied speech." Consequently, then,
the opposite has to be true.
Even the arising of the intent towards
unbeneficial qualities is not very
helpful, let alone following those thoughts in
let alone following those thoughts in
body and speech.
So, that's why you should give rise to
following intents, following choices.
Like, I intend to choose rightly
when presented with cruelty, killing, uh
stealing, all the precepts,
non-celibacy, uh negligence, faithlessness,
uh negligence, faithlessness,
shamelessness, imprudence, un- being
unlearned, I will choose the opposite.
I will maintain the intent to choose the
right thing, to abstain from the pull
uh of the grain with the with the with
the current of all these unskillful
choices.
And then what it gives us uh the
example, it's like um
"Chunda, suppose there was an uneven
path and another even path to circumvent
it. Or suppose there's an uneven ford and
Or suppose there's an uneven ford and
another even ford to circumvent it. In
the same way, a cruel individual
circumvents the cruelty by not being
cruel. There is no third option.
Or let me let me do a bit of both and
find my way out of it.
So, these are the binary choices when it
comes to That's why they boil down to
this core of the of the intent. Cruelty,
ill will, sensual desire, hindrances
because there is no middle ground there.
You're either allowing the animal to
control you,
accepting the given options, pressures,
stuff that's been speaking into your
ear, or not and maintaining perspective in
or not and maintaining perspective in
face of it.
It's not very complex, but yeah.
It doesn't mean it's easy.
Um
It says, "An individual who is attached
to his own views, holding them tight,
refusing to let them go, circle vents it
by not being attached to his own views,
not holding them tight by letting them
go easily." So, how do you let go of the
views? Well, by questioning them.
Are you blindly defending the
uh standpoints and views because they
provide you with a sense of safety,
uh confidence,
or are you willing
at any given moment to question your
views? If a question presents itself, you won't
If a question presents itself, you won't
shy away from it. You will follow it
through even if it proves that you were
completely wrong in the core of your
being for what you believed in.
That's how you overcome your views.
So, Chunda, all unbeneficial qualities
lead downwards while all beneficial
qualities lead upwards.
In the same way, a cruel individual
goes upwards by not being cruel.
So, by exercising the right choices, the
mind's going upwards.
Um and then it goes to the um
the last bit. It's like um
If you're sinking in the mud yourself,
Chunda, it is quite impossible for you
to pull out someone else who is
also sinking in the mud.
But if you're not sinking in the mud
it is quite possible for you to pull out
someone else who's sinking in the mud.
So, if you are not tamed, trained,
quenched yourself, it is quite
impossible for you to help tame, train,
and quench someone else.
But if you are tamed, trained, and
quenched yourself, it is quite possible
for you to tame,
train, and quench somebody else.
I mean,
kind of common sense, you would think.
So, in the same way, a cruel individual
quenches by not being cruel.
So,
one quenches the mind, quenches the
mind, trains the mind,
develops the right view, has the mind
going upwards
by exercising, by maintaining the right
intent, i.e., the right context, and by
exercising the right choices on the
basis of that intent.
Which See, intent is already a choice.
You choose to ignore the context or not.
So, it's like a more general choice, on
account of which you will be either
exercising more specific choices that
are right,
that are that are going
um they're circum- circumventing the bad
ones. Um Um
and then
it says, "So, Chunda, I have told the
expositions of wearing away, arousing
intent, the way around, going up, and quenching.
the way around, going up, and quenching.
Out of compassion, I have done what
teachers should do
who wants
uh
what a teacher should do who wants what
is best for his disciples. Here the
roots of trees, here the empty huts
develop jhana, Chunda. Do not be
negligent and not regret it later. This
is my instruction."
Uh oh, by the way, this part develop
jhana, it's like jhana is just used as a
verb, really. It just means contemplate.
Um contemplate jhana, don't be
negligent. Doesn't mean enter the first
jhana or something.
Uh, if you if you practice contemplation
rightly, correctly,
correctly,
surmount the unwholesome things,
withdraw them withdraw your mind from
them sufficiently, you will enter the
first comprehension as I like to call
it. Um,
Um,
on account of the wearing away, on
account of the right practice.
Um, and then, yeah, you'll know what to do
and then, yeah, you'll know what to do
rest.
So, then it says, "This is what the
auspicious one said." Pleased, venerable
Mahacunda delighted in what the Buddha
said. He says, "44 items have been stated,
He says, "44 items have been stated,
organized into five sections. Wearing in
the Wearing Away is the name of this
discourse discourse, which is as deep as
the ocean." It's kind of the
the core pretty much.
Uh, just ties into like even cuz you
know you had like you had those
complex Well, Well,
um,
same more kind of advanced higher types
of instructions, detailed expositions on
paticcasamuppada or this or that, which
you know would go over people's heads
generally. And then you had those instructions
And then you had those instructions
given to some monks and nuns, uh, go to
seclusion and anything that you know is
unbeneficial, don't cultivate it.
Anything you know is beneficial,
cultivate it. They did that for 3
months, came back arahants.
So, those
kind of polar opposites
on two different like ends of well, same
spectrum of right instruction, but very
two different like very far apart,
resulted in arahantship.
So, the detailed advanced expositions
result in arahantship for some, and then
just abandon the unbeneficial qualities.
That resulted in arahantship for
another. And this kind of sutta shows you how.
And this kind of sutta shows you how.
It It It It shows you what's in common
to both, which is basically
that core principle
of
exercising the skillful choice at the
expense of the unskillful one by body,
speech, and mind.
So, you have to be aware of the choice.
That's why I keep saying, like, yes, you
can take on the precepts because the
authority told you so and it can help
you in the beginning. But, if it's kept
at the arms length,
if it's kept as a as a duty that I must
blindly adhere to and never allow my
mind to, you know, think about it. And
maybe highlight that there is always a choice.
highlight that there is always a choice.
As I said, at any given point you can
get up and not be a monk anymore.
Does that choice scare you thinking
about it?
Does the mind get wild when that's when
that option's presented? Means you are
not training anything. You're just
keeping it down, covered up.
So, that's why it's not just enough to
memorize these 44
items and then just uh automatically always
and then just uh automatically always
choose right. The choice needs to be
felt. Needs to be so it's something you need
Needs to be so it's something you need
to be conscious of. Like, oh, I could
actually it's 50/50. I could get up and leave,
it's 50/50. I could get up and leave,
but I choose not to.
I could say something unwholesome, but I
choose not to.
That's the that's the missing kind of um
aspect, angle in people's practice, with
people that who who keep the precepts
and do everything rightly, but still
don't have the right view.
Means they're doing it through silabbata
paramasa. They're doing it at the arms
length.
They're doing it kind of
well, through at least a degree of
avoiding of responsibility for that core
choice that you could stop doing it in
any given moment.
So, yes, you can use the environment, use
yes, you can use the environment, use
tradition, use the learning, use all of
that. Okay, I'll take on the precepts in
that sense, but not to shy away or mask
the choice
that you have every day to maintain it
or abandon it, to practice or not, but
to actually be able to come closer to it
without your mind overwhelming you in a
kind of
excitement towards the prospect of
letting it loose.
So, that's that level, the right level
of endurance and the right level of
choice, which obviously you have to be patient
which obviously you have to be patient
about. You can't just
decide the right level where you're
going to decide the right things. It
needs to be discerned.
When I say, "What do all these things
converge upon?" They converge upon the
choice. That's what's in common to all
those things. It's the fact that it's
your choice.
Others may do it like this.
We won't do it here.
Like, almost like we, as in like me and
my own mind. Hey, look, two of us, we're
not doing this.
Others will be non-celibate, we won't
be. Others will be negligent, we won't do
Others will be negligent, we won't do
that.
So, I'm choosing for both of us,
so to speak.
Um Ajahn, does this mean that the Buddha
answered Venerable Tun this question,
"If the fundamentals are enough?" Yes,
but you need to drill them in, or no,
there is more to it.
I know just purification of the body and
speech, but by mind as well. Well, yeah.
Yeah, it's like
the views are not going to
um automatically fall off just if
somebody's, as I say, virtuous,
um keeping the precepts and so on.
Like, the effort needs to be made with
like right contemplation, diligence in
regard to hindrances, in regard to all
the, you know, unwholesome choices that
carry the roots of of
uh greedy diversion, distraction. So,
yeah, like well, there is more to it,
yes, but not like more to it you do
something else. It's just there is more
of the same thing, but it needs to be
done like on the mental level
uh
well, without any tolerance for
exceptions.
So, that's why it's gradual. You know,
you will not just magically be able to
like keep your mind above sensual
desire. It's like so, you start physically.
It's like so, you start physically.
Well, keep your body out of the sensual
desire. So, you start verbally at the
verbal aspect. Okay, well, don't talk
about it. Don't be like spreading
gossip. Don't be engaging in all these
other compensating practices.
And then comes the point that it's like,
"Oh, yeah, I can see that mental choice
now cuz I haven't been obviously
muddying the water through like coarse
physical or verbal actions."
Now, the choice of those thoughts
enduring in your mind is presented, and
he's like, "Oh, I don't have to pick
them up, actually." In the same sense, I
don't have to pick things up with my
hand when they're in front of me. I
don't have to destroy them. I just need
to not pick it up.
Now, I see the same principle mentally.
Thoughts have arisen. I don't have to
pick them up. I don't have to get rid of
them. I don't have to do anything about
them. I just
don't have to pick them up. And I'm free
from them.
But in order for that mental choice to
become apparent, yeah, the the the right
physical and verbal choices need to be
cultivated well, sufficiently long. How
long that is, well, person will see.
There's not like a preset time.
Uh Ajahn, this might be related to the
last question. Uh does the first part of
the sutta suggest that people can get to
the eighth jhana without right view? You
eighth jhana without right view? You
mean like the four material um
attainment? Um
Um
uh Well, yes, other suttas do say that.
A person can
withdraw their mind rightly
and um develop first, second, third,
fourth jhana and then the subsequent
immaterial um
um
establishments of the mind.
Uh
But again,
even those people without the right view
would be um walking along the right
lines. So, they might not technically
So, they might not technically
have had enough right instruction to see
through their conceit in the sense of I
am in that subtle way,
but the only way to enter the first
jhana or go further is through
abandoning sensuality, not like anagami,
like um
but withdrawing your mind, completely
drying it from sensuality internally,
uh overcoming the five hindrances,
again, not like an arahant, um
permanently, but at least to the extent
that you've been diligently practicing
the way out of those things through
understanding them.
Not through like self-hypnotizing or
something where you are unaware of those
things. Because again, how can you
Because again, how can you
how can you be exercising right choices
as the sutta describe and says this is
what wearing away actually is, that even
jhana is the result of,
if you are hypnotized, if you're if
you're unaware of the options, if you're
completely oblivious
to the context, to the intent, to what
to choose, what's presented, and what
mind leans towards?
That's why any That's what I keep
saying, like any types of um
self-hypnosis or practice is just taking
away from where the actual work is done.
And see, even the ones that have entered
in the first jhana,
according to all the suttas, with
thinking and pondering
and joy born of withdrawal from the
unwholesome states. So, the knowledge
that you are safe from the threat, safe
from debt, safe from prison, safe from
danger. So, in order to know that you are safe
So, in order to know that you are safe
from the danger,
well, the only way to know that you the
only way to be safe from the danger and
feel that safety is to fully understand
the extent of danger, not to pretend
that it's not there cuz you're focused
on your
kneecaps or something. I don't know.
So, yes, people can technically get
jhanas without the right view, but
again, today the only actual
knowledge of jhanas, yes, okay, like
putting aside of the contemporary later
interpretations and stuff like that, but
sooner or later people would basically
fall back onto the suttas cuz that's
where the idea of jhana comes from.
So, that somebody can actually practice
the jhanas rightly, follow the jhanas
rightly, and attain the jhanas rightly
without having understood the
importance, the emphasis, the training
aspect of citta through these right
choices, that's not possible.
Technically, it's possible that somebody
was doing it back in the day cuz there
were lots of not as wrong instructions,
but today that somebody can arrive at
that without having come across the
right instruction of the Buddha in the
suttas, it's highly unlikely, let's say
like that.
So, if somebody were to develop the the the
if somebody were to develop the the the
the first jhana or higher, it has to be
developed through the exercising of the
same right choices, same withdrawal from
the same unwholesome things. So,
they'll almost certainly get the right
view even before their jhana, pretty much.
Um the next question,
I don't there is a
an intellectual understanding of the
principles. However, sometimes due to undeveloped
However, sometimes due to undeveloped
mindfulness, the choices seem to have
been made for you on some sense.
What can we do to develop the right How
can the choices be made for you?
That's not possible. Choice cannot be
made for you. You can certainly have a
very uh
weighty options.
Some options will be pressing you and
threatening you more than others.
But no choice can be made for you.
Ever.
Then it's not a choice.
And that's what people are afraid of,
basically. Once you start
Once you start
approaching everything through the
recognition of the of your choices,
it can get very scary very quickly cuz
you realize
well, nothing obliges you to live or
die. No external criteria, no external
No external criteria, no external
reason, no external You choose them to
You choose those things as reasons, but
you could then also choose them
to stop being reasons, basically, for
whatever you're doing or not doing.
That's why like the
uh um
in existential philosophy, Sartre was
referring to it, I remember, as a one
once a person takes on the take kind of
existential responsibility, I
start taking responsibility for the
choices and recognize that there is
never that that it's actually impossible for
that that it's actually impossible for
choice to be made for you.
You are the one accepting it or not.
He called it as monstrous freedom.
In other words, when you recognize how
free you actually are,
it can be overwhelmingly uh frightful,
scary. Because, yeah, at any given moment,
Because, yeah, at any given moment,
anybody can just get up and walk out
from anything.
And yeah, that's scary.
But that's something you you have to get
used to.
Like getting closer to the recognition that
getting closer to the recognition that
choice always rests with you mentally.
No matter the options,
no matter the weight of those options,
no matter the repercussions, no matter
the consequences,
choice cannot be made for you.
And that's again something I remember
like it's get get gets casually chanted
like in the monasteries and stuff like,
"Oh, we are the owners of our karma."
And it's like
people don't realize the extent of that.
And they think like, "Oh, yeah, we are
the owners of" It's like, no, karma is
choice. Every action is intention.
So, there is no action without a choice.
So, choice it's already
something that pretty much sets and
determines your karma. Just as the sutra
says, like, just the rising of
beneficial or unbeneficial intent.
It's already
taking you up or taking you down. Let
alone following through with body
um and speech
and actions.
So, the the the common casual chant,
"Well, we are the owners of our
actions." Like, yeah,
through and through,
all the way.
Your action to choose to your choice to
choose to get up and continue living
your life the way you live your life,
that's your karma.
Your choice to change, to do something
about it, well, that's your karma.
It's like, "Oh, do you recognize how far
that goes?"
Nothing. There's nothing that can come
in between you and that freedom.
And the sooner you recognize that, the
sooner you admit it, more importantly,
well, the sooner you can cheetah stop
being afraid from it off it. It will It
will get used to it. It can be
overwhelming in the beginning, but
that's why you have the precepts.
They're preventing you from spiraling
into the unwanted directions on account
of the same freedom
of choice.
Uh
and then the mind get can get can settle
in that. Can get used to that. And it
won't be as frightening.
Cuz it's not a surprise anymore.
And that's where the training becomes
elevated. It's like, now you can
It's like, now you can
you can get closer to that edge of
freedom and really purify it.
Really develop
uh the right intent, maintain that right
intent, right context.
And then all the all the presented
options to choose
to choose
is 44 unwholesome things or 44
opposites. You will know what to choose.
You will know what to choose.
You will know what to emphasize, you
will know what not to like tolerate and
give in and add more fuel to it.
And it's the same instruction, same
principle that would have started from
the from the beginning like in the say
early stages of training. And this is
already now the higher refinement of
your cheetah. It's the same thing.
That's why as I said in some of the
suttas that all people needed to become
arahants. Cuz the same principle goes all the way
Cuz the same principle goes all the way
through.
So regarding this last question, you
could see that
due to the undeveloped mindfulness, the
choices seem to have been made for you.
So you chose lack of mindfulness.
And that's why subsequent choices felt
automatic. But
But
if you didn't choose the
uh lack of mindfulness
abandonment of the context willingly
those choices would have remain
uh seen.
Not just submitted to.
So again
nothing nothing can come between you and
your responsibility for
everything choose, big or small.
I don't know. I think you mentioned
before that one usually tries to get rid
of one hindrance through um
another hindrance and that's how one
ends up accepting some hindrance.
Could you speak more about this? Uh
Uh
I don't quite remember what what was the
context of that, but uh
I think I just meant basically a person
is just acting out of hindrances
cuz they're trying to get rid of the
entire options presented.
options presented.
Let's put it that way in the context of
today's talk.
So, the problem with hindrances
Uh for example, maybe there's a version
of aversion to that aversion and try to
get rid of it.
Well, you can have aversion to your
aversion. But um
But um
yeah, you might not be able to help
that, but it's like do you go about in
the right way or the wrong way?
Are you trying to get rid of the choices
of aversion, i.e. your cheetah, that's
affected with aversion?
Or are you recognizing that that's the
arisen state of things? As the sutta
says, he knows the mind of anger as mind
of anger, mind of lust as mind of lust,
not he he tries to change it and wrestle
it and tackle it and get rid of it and
and tailor it to his liking. Yeah.
No. Knowledge is the way you tailor it
to your liking, knowing it for what it
is. So, you have a mind of aversion, you
So, you have a mind of aversion, you
know that the the choices to to speak,
to say something, to do something on
account of this aversion are bound.
Those those options are your state of
mind. So, you're not trying to get rid of
So, you're not trying to get rid of
that.
Instead, you are choosing to not accept
the aversion while it's there. That's
the subtle difference.
And why is that difference important?
Cuz that's where your choice is. See, it
would be easier if I could just remove
the tempting things, including my mind
states, so I don't have to feel the edge
of the choice.
And that's that's why people fail to
free themselves from hindrances and just
end up from one falling into the other
or
going in circles basically and then
developing a view that pretty much
um
self-induced to oblivion of hypnosis and
half-asleep state of concentrations is
the only possible peace they can know.
Because either mind bothers you or
you're not aware of it.
There is no third option.
So, that's why again
others will be cruel, others will be
non-self, others will follow sensuality.
All of these are listed things in this
sutta are options that citta will come up with
are options that citta will come up with
through interaction with the senses and
so on. It's like, but I will choose not
to.
I will not add fuel. I will not add
further choices of this that would then
kind of start [snorts] adding towards
the actions by body and speech and so
on. Doesn't matter how long the possibility
Doesn't matter how long the possibility
for cruelty remains.
for non-self liberacy remains.
For negligence remains.
That's not up to you.
Up to you is to no exceptions. You not
You don't accept it and you don't fuel
it. So, that's the difference.
So, that's the difference.
When I say one tries to get rid of the
hindrance means one tries to get rid of
the entire
experience as a whole. The mind, oh this
is unpleasant, this is unwholesome. I
read all the suttas, Buddha says it's
unwholesome. I must get rid of it. I
must make this whole thing go away.
And um
and then usually those those um
those suttas where the Buddha talks
about like this
somebody who already sees the citta,
somebody who's already sought upon you
know like that um
the five ways of stealing your thoughts.
It's like the uh hobby cheetah training.
So, somebody who's already been
exercising the right choices and doing
things on the right level, recognizes
cheetah the animal for what it is,
then he can refine it in those other
five ways.
But, without seeing your cheetah, those
five ways just become five excuses to
try to get rid of the things cuz they
bother you and you're already averse
towards the whole experience.